<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Esoptron basilikon. Or A kenning-glasse for a Christian king Taken out of the 19. chapter of the gospell of Saint Iohn, the 5. verse, in the words 3 Behold the man. And treated on by William Thorne, Deane of Chichester, and his Maiesties Hebrew reader in the Vniuersity of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Thorne, William, 1568 or 9-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113932</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849160</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849160</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13745)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14296)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1696:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Esoptron basilikon. Or A kenning-glasse for a Christian king Taken out of the 19. chapter of the gospell of Saint Iohn, the 5. verse, in the words 3 Behold the man. And treated on by William Thorne, Deane of Chichester, and his Maiesties Hebrew reader in the Vniuersity of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Thorne, William, 1568 or 9-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by R. R[ead] for Iohn Harrison [2], dwelling in Pater-noster-rowe, at the signe of the Anchor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and identification of publisher from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14296:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Or A Kenning-Glaſſe for a <hi>Chriſtian King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TAKEN OVT OF THE 19. Chapter of the Goſpell of Saint Iohn, <hi>the</hi> 5. <hi>verſe, in theſe words;</hi> BEHOLD THE MAN.</p>
            <p>And Treated on by <hi>William Thorne,</hi> Deane <hi>of</hi> Chicheſter, <hi>and his Maieſties</hi> Hebrew Reader in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie of</hi> Oxford.</p>
            <q>VEHASENNEH BOGNER BAESH VEHASENNEH. <bibl>VEELLE-SHEMOTH 3:2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON Imprinted by R.R. for <hi>Iohn Harriſon,</hi> dwelling in Pater-noſter-rowe, at the ſigne of the Anchor. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:14296:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>IN DEFENCE</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14296:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST mightie Monarch, and <hi>puiſſant Prince,</hi> IAMES, of England, Scotland, France, and <hi>Ireland, King, defender of the</hi> Faith, &amp;c. Grace, Mercie, and <hi>Peace from him, which was,</hi> and which is, and which <hi>is to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Praeſume not (Dread Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) in this <hi>praefixed Title,</hi> to praeſcribe praecepts politike to any Chriſtian Prince, much leſſe vnto your Sacred Maieſtie. Should I attempt any ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, it would appeare in me <hi>Annibalem Phormio,</hi> as the Adage is, and I were much out of mine Element. This is a proiect more fitting, ſo high, and Mightie a Prince, as you are,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Apop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegms.</hi>
               </note> and alreadie in that your <hi>Kinglie Gift</hi> to a King moſt abſolutely performed. As <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaid of that very ſame word: ſo may we of that your worke, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. What is it then, which in this <hi>Inſcription</hi> of mine I would
<pb facs="tcp:14296:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo faine inſinuate to my Lord, and King? VVhat but that he alwayes be like himſelfe? that he read himſelfe as it were, &amp; rule out of his owne booke? Admit then (moſt Chriſtian King) thou ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedſt in perfection (as I pray God thou maieſt) all Chriſtian Princes vpon earth; admit no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained, whom thou mighteſt imitate;<note n="*" place="margin">August: <hi>on theſe words;</hi> The Iust ſhall ſee, &amp;c. Pſal. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ipſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus tibi remanet;</hi> there remaines yet for thee <hi>The Imitation of Christ. Beholde the man.</hi> Loe here is<note n="‖" place="margin">A Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Glaſſe for a Chriſtian King. <hi>Hom: Iliad</hi> 1. <hi>Val: Mar:</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>A Kenning-Glaſſe for a Chriſtian King.</hi> As out of thoſe three verſes of <hi>Homer</hi> the Author therof expreſſed (he ſaid) the very liuing <hi>Image</hi> of Ioue</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo forth: So <hi>this Inſcription</hi> I extract out of theſe three words of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.5. The firſt Booke. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 17.18.19. &amp;c. <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Behold the man.</hi> As thou art a Chriſtian, ſo is this a <hi>Common Glaſſe</hi> to thee (O King) with all other Chriſtians, as in the firſt Diuiſion of the third generall Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this text, and third diſtinction I haue de-declared: As thou art a King, ſo doth it (out <hi>of thine ovvne mouth</hi>) more properlie concerne thee; Aſwell for that a <hi>King is to compute</hi> vnto God for each Chriſtian ſoule in his whole Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale: as that <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. <hi>24.2.</hi> Ecclus. <hi>10.2.3.</hi> Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ad Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. Plat. in polit. Regis ad exempu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Cl. Claud: de <hi>4.</hi> conſulat. Henorij.</note> 
               <hi>vvhole Common-vveale</hi> is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie conformed vnto the cuſtomes of her King. And therefore of choiſe I conſecrate it vnto thy Chriſtian, and Kinglie calling. Accept then in good part (moſt Gracious King) this thy poore Schollers praeſent. <hi>Chriſtus tibi liber exemplaris est.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. <hi>13.15.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Conſtant. ad Sanctorum coetum Orat. c. <hi>12.</hi> in Euſebius.</note> I haue giuen thee (ſaith Chriſt) an <hi>example.</hi> He is an <hi>euerlaſting example</hi> for thee: Imitate him, and thy ſubiects will imitate thee. He is a moſt<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Phalereus <hi>to</hi> Ptolome <hi>in</hi> Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Exemplar ſtates-booke</hi> for thee: Read him,
<pb facs="tcp:14296:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> and thy Subiects will reade thee. He is a <hi>Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Magiſtrates</hi> for thee, <hi>A Kenning-Glaſſe for Kings:</hi> aſſimilate thy ſelfe vnto him, and thy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects will aſſimilate themſelues vnto thee.<note place="margin">Chryſost:</note> And this is, the Office and vſe of this <hi>Glaſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>JAMES the Minor</hi> (ſaith one) was very,<note place="margin">Ludolph: de vita Ieſu Chriſti, part. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>59</hi> Galat. <hi>1.19</hi> frater Ieſu Ioſeph: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>20.</hi> Euſeb: Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt: hiſt: <hi>2.1.</hi>
               </note> very like <hi>Christ in face:</hi> and for that cauſe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially (the ſaid writer ſurmizeth) he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Lords brother.</hi> I diſpute not of the one, or the other, of, or on. It ſeemes he was well ſeene in this <hi>Spirituall Glaſſe:</hi> Elſe whence in his face are thoſe rayes of virtues? his <hi>Humilitie?</hi> for he vvas called<note n="*" place="margin">Iacobus Minor Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph: <hi>as afore. So</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen.</note> 
               <hi>IAMES the leſſe.</hi> His <hi>Iuſtice?</hi> for he was called<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ex Hegeſipp: comment. <hi>5.</hi> Euſeb. <hi>2.23</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>IAMES the iust.</hi> His all manner of virtues? for ſo I ſuppoſe, when Chriſt ſaid vnto him;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Iames</hi> 1.23 <hi>Iames</hi> 2.1.4.9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>Learne of me,</hi> for I am humble and meeke: he learned him with humilitie all manner of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</p>
            <p>Good King, will it pleaſe thee to conſider not ſleightly, as did <hi>that man</hi> in Saint <hi>Iames</hi> his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall face, but ſeriouſlie thy <hi>Spirituall face</hi> in this <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> did? wilt thou compare, and compoſe the cariage of thy whole life according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie? <hi>Thy Greatneſſe</hi> muſt vouchſafe to do then, as this <hi>Iames</hi> the <hi>Minor,</hi> as this <hi>James the Iuſt</hi> did: thou muſt out of thy Iuſtice diſtributiue go on in Gods name, as thou haſt begun: thou muſt, as <hi>A iust STE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARD,</hi> diuide aequallie; to thy ſelfe thine owne, to the Common weale her owne, to the Church her owne, <hi>impartiallie,</hi> without <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of perſons:</hi> thou muſt ſcourge out all <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polye-mongers,</hi> and ſuch like monſters out of thy common-weale: as <hi>Chriſt did thoſe Money-chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> out of his Church: thou muſt ſuppreſſe all
<pb facs="tcp:14296:4"/> Church-robbing-Chriſt-robbing Satans,<note place="margin">Th' Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles in <hi>VV: Rufus. Iames</hi> 1.27 <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 49.23. <hi>August. de Ciuit: Dei.</hi> 5 24.25. &amp;c. <hi>Iames</hi> 2.8. <hi>Iames.</hi> 4.10 Of <hi>Iames</hi> of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Euſeb: Hiſt: Eccleſiast.</hi> 2.23. <hi>De Imitat: Chriſti</hi> W: Th: <hi>à cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis.</hi> 3.55. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 15.17 <hi>Pſa.</hi> 82.6.7 <hi>Amos</hi> 6.12 13.</note> ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee; <hi>So ſvveete is the bread of Christ:</hi> and a daintie foode for Kings. To be <hi>a Father vnto the fatherleſſe,</hi> an husband to the widowes, <hi>a Foſter-father</hi> vnto the Church of Chriſt, <hi>Hae tibi erunt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes;</hi> — Here is thy glorie (O King) <hi>Si Iuſtus imperas,</hi> if thou fulfill the <hi>Royall lavve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of thy Humilitie likewiſe, thou muſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>cast dovvne thy ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>kneele,</hi> and <hi>Camell</hi> thy <hi>knees</hi> before the Lord thy maker, for thy ſinnes, and for the ſinnes of thy people: thou muſt ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme thy ſelfe <hi>ſo much, and no more,</hi> as God aeſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thee; thou muſt be <hi>little</hi> in thine owne eyes. In ſhort thou muſt reiect thy many flatterers, that will ſay; <hi>Thou art a God;</hi> and reſpect thy fewe friends, that will tell thee; <hi>Thou art a man.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. — I haue ſaid; <hi>Yee are Gods,</hi> but yee ſhall dye like men. This is indeed to be <hi>James the leſſe,</hi> this is the way to be <hi>James the Great,</hi> this is indeed to be <hi>James the Iust.</hi> Doe this, and thou doſt rightlie, <hi>Behold the man:</hi> do this, and thou doſt rightly contemplate Chriſt. This is that then, which I was ſo faine to inſinuate vnto thee, my Liege Lord, and King, induced hereto, in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, as your ſubiect, in ſpeciall, as your Prieſt, and Scholler: As a Prieſt in way of conſcience I choſe to do this, as knowing <hi>Amaziah</hi> of old, what he ſaid vnto <hi>Amos; O, thou the Seer,</hi> go, flee thou away into the land of <hi>Judah,</hi> and there eate thy bread, and Propheſie there. But Propheſie no more at <hi>Beth—el.</hi> For it is <hi>the Kings Chappell,</hi> and <hi>the Kings Court.</hi> As your Scholler in all conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings</hi> 1.39.40.</note> I could not chooſe but doe this; Amidſt our <hi>great</hi> Oxford <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to adde <hi>my Aramites
<pb facs="tcp:14296:4"/> crie</hi> to, <hi>Malco legnolemin cheife;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.4. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 1.31 <hi>Prou:</hi> 8.15. <hi>Prou.</hi> 21.1.</note> God ſaue <hi>my Lord King James</hi> for euer.</p>
            <p>Now the very God of heauen, and earth (<hi>in vvhoſe hands</hi> are Kingdoms, and the hearts of Kings) confirme your <hi>Maieſties Throne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 89.36.37.</note> as the <hi>Sunne</hi> in heauen, and the <hi>Throne</hi> of your <hi>Sonne,</hi> as <hi>the Moone</hi> for euermore. Direct your hearts and handes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.71.72.</note> that you may <hi>ſeede your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Jacob,</hi> according to the Simplicitie of your hearts, and guide your <hi>inheritance in Iſrael</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diſcretion of your hands:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17.14 &amp; 19.16.</note> and graunt you both Grace, and your ſeed after you, alwayes to haue this <hi>Kenning-Glaſſe</hi> afore your eyes; Euen <hi>The King of Kings,</hi> and Lord of Lords.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſſe most</hi> humble Scholler, <hi>William Thorne.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14296:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14296:5"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Search the Scriptures. In the 19. Chapter of the Goſpell according to S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> the 5. verſe, it is thus written; <hi>And he ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, Beholde the man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 19. ch: of the Goſpell according to S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> the 5. verſe, the latter part of the 5. verſe; <hi>And he ſaid vnto them, Beholde the man.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words of holy writ, which now I read vnto you (Reuerend, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded in Chriſt Ieſus) It will pleaſe you to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, and <hi>note with me</hi> firſt,<note place="margin">The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.</note> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally theſe three principall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Firſt <hi>the perſon by whom</hi> they were vttered: Secondly <hi>to whom;</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>manner</hi> thereof: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>of whome,</hi> together with the <hi>matter.</hi> The particulars that occurre (as many
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14296:6"/> there are) they ſhall be touched rather then handled in their place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <note place="margin">The firſt generall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note>Firſt as touching the <hi>perſon</hi> by whom they were vttered; <hi>Some argue</hi> by God the Father Almightie himſelfe, and that it was he that ſaid vnto them; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the man: As if he</hi> would haue ſaid; This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which you ſee now ſtanding here in this pittifull plight, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning indeed was God, of the ſame diuine eſſence, and ſubſtance, as I am; mine onely ſonne, the expreſſe image of my ſelfe, being his naturall father; And yet behold for you men, and for your ſaluation from your ſinnes, I ſent him down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to earth; content (as you ſee) to clad himſelfe with the mantle of your mortalitie, inſteed of the garment of his owne glorie. For I haue decreed this cup ſhall not paſſe away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; my decree ſhal ſtand: Loe how I haue loued your ſaluation; loe how I haue loathed your ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Or it may</hi> be probable rather our bleſſed Sauiour ſaid it of himſelfe; <hi>As
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14296:6"/> if he would</hi> haue ſaid; Behold in what place, and what caſe I am; a miſerable man, a ſcorne of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, indeed a worme, and no man: Conſider it is not for my ſelfe I ſuffer this, but for your ſakes; for which to do you good, I wil lay down mine owne ſoule to: only I deſire this fauour at your hands; crucifie not the ſonne of man againe; let it ſuffize that I be onely once offered on the croſſe for you, <hi>Semelimmolatus eſt,</hi> &amp; ſo forth.<note place="margin">De conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. <hi>2.</hi> Can. ſemel Immolatus eſt.</note> 
               <hi>But the whole</hi> current of Interpreters, as alſo the circumſtance of the place ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it eſpecially as ſpoken by <hi>Pilat,</hi> of whom alſo like mention is made in the verſe next immediatly going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; Then <hi>Pilat</hi> went forth againe, &amp; ſaid vnto them; Behold I bring him forth vnto you, and ſo forth: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto may be added the authorities of all tranſlations: In the Syriacke Metaphraſe of the new Teſtament, and according to that in the correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edſt copies of the French, and Italian, and Spaniſh Bibles, as alſo in ſome
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14296:7"/> Engliſh editions the name of <hi>Pilate</hi> is praeciſely put downe <hi>Vemar Lehun Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latús,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Metaphr. Syriac. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, And <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid vnto them.</p>
            <p>Vnto<note n="a" place="margin">The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note> them? vnto whome? For ſo it followeth in the ſecond circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance I ſpeake a word, or two, and it ſhall be but a word, of the <hi>perſons, or parties, to whom</hi> it was vttered; It was vttered vnto the Iewes. But is God a God of the Iewes onely, and not of the Gentiles alſo?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29.</note> Yes <hi>of the Gentiles alſo: Tros Rutuluſue fuat;</hi> all is one. And therefore at that time alike vnto the Iewes, &amp; to the Gentiles both, it was aequally ſaid; <hi>Behold the man.</hi> But was Chriſt then Chriſt, and is he not now? Yes <hi>Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday,</hi> and to day,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.8.</note> &amp; the ſame for euer. And therfore eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then this was written alſo for our inſtruction, and we were the men to whom it was ſaid, <hi>Behold the man.</hi> Yea this ſhall be written for <hi>the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.19.</note> and the children yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne ſhall behold the man.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14296:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Now</hi> for the <hi>intention of the ſpeaker,</hi> and <hi>manner of the ſpeach.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen on <hi>Math.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> vpon that interrogatorie of <hi>Pilate, Math:</hi> 27. Art thou the King of the Iewes? <hi>Perchance</hi> (ſaith he) he asked him <hi>deridingly,</hi> perchance doubtingly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance axiomatically, or affirmatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.<note place="margin">Rupert: on <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Rupertus</hi> the Abbat vpon theſe very words; <hi>Behold the man:</hi> &amp; againe behold your King, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19. <hi>Let Pilate ſay</hi> (ſaith he) what he wil, let him beare the ſimpler ſort in hand, that al that he doth againſt Chriſt, he doth againſt his will; But <hi>ita locuto non credet Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana ſeueritas: His inner parts</hi> are full of hypocriſie, diſſimulation, and mockerie.<note place="margin">The Engliſh Marginals.</note> Our Engliſh Marginals vpon the ſame, and the like places, harpe much vpon the ſame ſtring.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> if that were true, and were reputed for ſuch a treacherie in <hi>Pilate;</hi> what ſhall we recken of ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians now a dayes?<note place="margin">☞</note> How many are there amongſt vs (a ſhame to ſpeake it) euen in this noone day of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14296:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> that make a trade of it to play <hi>Pilate,</hi> hooding themſelues with hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie like vnto that Roman, that <hi>neuer ſaid, that which he thought,</hi> nor neuer thought that which he ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I defend him not in this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I praeſume the very name of <hi>Pilate</hi> is vngracious, and odious in Chriſtian mens ears. Nay I ſay farther, the whole proceſſe of this his iudgement was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al iuſtice.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 27.4 <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.47.</note> For he conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned him that was <hi>innocent and iust:</hi> againſt his owne ſcience &amp; conſcience to. For he knew of himſelfe, or he had warning els of his wife,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 27.19. &amp; 24.</note> that <hi>he ſhould haue</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with that iuſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Againſt the loue of God, for the feare of man. For he was afraide leaſt otherwiſe he ſhould <hi>not be Caeſars friend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.12.</note> or at leaſt wiſe leſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> would not be his friend: &amp; rather then ſo he left to loue Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Panorm: in pract: iſtis praemiſſis.</note>Yet be-lye we not the deuill <hi>Si dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolus eſſet in iudicio vt reus</hi> (as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that great Canoniſt to inſtance) if the deuil himſelfe were ſummoned to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14296:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> the court for this, or that crime, <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad hoc,</hi> a defence might not be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the diuell; how much more may <hi>Pilat</hi> anſwear for himſelf? For if <hi>Pilat</hi> of his own inclination had bin ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to had done him to death, what needed he to haue vſed any ſuch vaine gloſſe or praetence? what to pleaſe the Iewes? but he knew well inough he could not pleaſe them better, then by diſpatching him out of the way; what to collude with the almightie? but he was not ignorant that God neither vſeth to deceiue, nor to be deceiued:
<q>Lapides, &amp; ligna loquuntur.</q> For it was written on the croſſe with a mans pen: &amp; it was writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Hebrew,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt: Auguſt. on Iohn the 19.</note> that the Iews the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glozing on the law: in Greeke, that the Gentiles then glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in their wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Latin that the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gouerning the world: that al the world might know that <hi>Pilat</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged Chriſt <hi>to be Ieſus of Naz: King of the Iewes.</hi> For ſo alſo when the high Prieſts wold haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouled him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14296:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Write not King</hi> of the Iewes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.21.22</note> but that he ſaid, I am King of the Iewes, <hi>Pilate</hi> anſwered; what I haue written, I haue written.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt:</hi> on this place.</note> 
               <hi>Ideó enim Pilatus ſcripſit quod ſcripſit, quia dominus dixit, quod dixit.</hi> I conclude therefore both by theſe, and other Scriptures, as alſo by other conferences of my text, that in this place it was <hi>Pilates</hi> intent to haue mooued commiſeration, and to haue ſet Chriſt free: And therfore when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the cuſtome of the Iewes hee had ſcourged him, when hee had ſuffered the barbarous ſouldiers to make a foole of him, to clap a purple robe on his backe, to plat a crowne of thornes on his head, to put a reede in his right hand, to ſpitte on him, to ſmite him with roddes; then euen then he praeſented him a very ſpectacle of calamity to to the cruell harted Iewes; if perhaps by any miſeries, by any meanes they might relent, and he ſaid vnto them; Behold the man; <hi>As if he would</hi> haue
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14296:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaid, if you be good men haue mercy of this innocent man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt:</hi> on this place.</note> or if you bee men take ſome pittie of a man: <hi>Etſi Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inuidetis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) parcite, quia ſubiectum videtis:</hi> and if hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you enuyed him, whilſt you ſaid he was a king, yet ſpare him now at length, ſith you ſee him a <hi>ſubiect,</hi> nay an <hi>abiect man: Ferueſcit ignominia, fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſcat inuidia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O the ineffable operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, euen in the harts of infidels,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt:</hi> all along.</note> that the wife of a Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tile ſhould ſee in her ſleep, which the whole natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iewes could not ſee being awake: that the Gentiles ſhould be more compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate to Chriſt-ward, then the Iews: that <hi>Pilate</hi> a Pagan ſhould be the firſt proclaimer of that, which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied ſo long ago; <hi>Ne corru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas tituli inſcriptionem:</hi> that it could not ſinke out of his head, but that this man (a man vnlike inough as they had made him) muſt needes be that ſame Ieſus of Nazareth king of the Iewes.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14296:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Doubtleſſe as <hi>Pilate</hi> wrote this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, or title in the Croſſe with his owne hand writing: ſo was it written afore alſo in the heart of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> though hee wiſt not when, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the finger of that truth her ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.38.</note> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he asked her, <hi>what ſhe was?</hi> And I am perſwaded it ſhall be eaſier for <hi>Pilate</hi> in the day of doome, then for thoſe peremptorie Iewes; for they <hi>Maius pecatum habent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.11.</note> Nay I pray God <hi>Pilate</hi> doe not riſe in iudgement with many of vs Chriſtians, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs then iuſtly, as then hee did Chriſt vniuſtly: for hee certainely would willingly not haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him: but we day by day, like thoſe reprobate Iewes, doe wilfully crye, as they did vnto <hi>Pilate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh:</hi> 19.15.</note> ſo we to our ſins, <hi>crucifie him, crucifie him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third generall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note>
               <hi>Thirdly to leaue</hi> the perſons by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to whom it was ſpoken, together with the manner of ſpeaking; the <hi>perſon of whome it</hi> was ſpoken, was Chriſt; the <hi>matter</hi> was this, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14296:10"/> the man. And firſt, Beholde.<note place="margin">The firſt diuiſion of the third generall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</note> Which word in holy Scripture hath diuers and ſundry ſignifications: but I encomber not your eares with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary notes. Onely I content you with this alone obſeruation of <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bernard on Math.</hi> 19. Behold we haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all &amp;c. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Whenſoeuer you read</hi> this word <hi>Behold,</hi> marke then (ſaith he) there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes enſueth ſome important mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: tis one way or other a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worde to a wonder. <hi>Behold a virgin</hi> ſhall conceiue, &amp; being forth a ſonne,<note place="margin">Pele. Eſa. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and you ſhal call his name <hi>Admirable,</hi> or <hi>Wonderfull, Eſay.</hi> 7. &amp; the .9.<note place="margin">The firſt diuiſion of the third generall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: the ſecond di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction. <hi>Irenaeus contr: Haer: Epiphan in panario. Auguſt: ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod vult:</hi> all along. <hi>Euſebius Cyrill</hi> euery where.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly behold a</hi> man, not a God only as <hi>Simon,</hi> and <hi>Cerdon,</hi> and <hi>Marcion</hi> maintaine; but <hi>a man;</hi> Not <hi>an aethereall man,</hi> paſſing through with a trice, through the wombe of the woman, as <hi>Valentine,</hi> and <hi>Bardiſan,</hi> and their pew fellowes haue plaide; but <hi>a man indeede.</hi> Not without <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption</hi> of humaine fleſh ſubſiſting as <hi>Eutyches</hi> excepts; Not without <hi>a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule aſsiſting,</hi> as Apollinaris
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14296:11"/> auoucheth:<note place="margin">Cic de nat: deor. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Not as the Epicure would haue it, <hi>Non corpus, ſed quaſi corpus,</hi> Not as hauing a body, but as it were a body: <hi>Non ſanguis, ſed quaſi ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guis,</hi> not a ſoule, but as it were a ſoule: Not <hi>a phantaſticall body,</hi> nor a kinde of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall blood, but a true, naturall, and ſubſtantiall body,<note place="margin">Creedes Nicen: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanas.</note> and blood: fleſh of her fleſh, and bone of her bone: <hi>Very God of very God,</hi> and very man, of very man, conſubſtantiall to God his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as touching his diuinity, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiall to <hi>Mary</hi> his mother as touching his <hi>inhumanation,</hi> or huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Cyrenſ: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: out of the reſt of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at large.</note>Or is it poſſible, (thinke we) that it was his <hi>paſsible</hi> humanity, that raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> from the dead? or that it was his <hi>impaſsible diuinitie</hi> that lamented <hi>Lazarus</hi> when he was dead? or that it was his <hi>humane pouerty,</hi> that with fiue Barley loaues, and a few fiſhes fed ſo many thouſand? or that it was his <hi>rich omnipotencie</hi> that fedde on a Fig-tree? or that it was <hi>the aeternall</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14296:11"/> 
               <hi>incorporeall</hi> worde, which in that ſtrange agony ſwet water, &amp; bloud? whoſe very ſoule was heauy vnto death? that in the houre of his death, and horror of his heart, cryed <hi>Eli, Eli, my God, my God?</hi> No, no, that was the ſonne of <hi>Mary,</hi> and as hee was the ſonne of <hi>Mary,</hi> as ſay <hi>Gela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> and <hi>Gregory;</hi> or that it was his <hi>mortall, and maſsie body</hi> that wrought miracles? caſt out diuells? cured all men of their maladies? came in at the doore, when the doore was ſhut? walked vpon waters as vpon drye land? <hi>cui venti, tempeſtateſquè obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundârunt,</hi> commaunding the winds <hi>peace,</hi> and the Seas <hi>bee ſtill?</hi> In a worde, that ſuſtained the world with his word? No verylie, this coulde not bee but the very ſonne of the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. Not God onely: for then he could not haue ſuffered that; Not man onely: for then hee coulde not haue doone this. Not God by himſelfe, and man by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14296:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> as the <hi>Quaternioniſts</hi> cauill;<note place="margin">C. de ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Trinit: Nos trade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen <hi>of the</hi> Orthodox <hi>faith.</hi>
               </note> profeſſing indeede the bleſſed Virgin to be <hi>Chriſoſtocos</hi> the mother of Chriſt the man, but not <hi>Theotocos</hi> the mother of Chriſt a God: Not Chriſt (I ſay) <hi>Alius &amp; alius</hi> two perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in an vnquoth nature:<note place="margin">Vincent: contr: Haer. c. <hi>19.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Athanſius <hi>in his Creed</hi> Greg: Naz: <hi>euery where.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>Aliud &amp; aliud</hi> (as <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſpeakes</hi>) two natures in one perſon: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> God and man, <hi>homo-deus, &amp; Deus-homo,</hi> as the ſchooleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teach.</p>
            <p>Of which his holy hypoſtaſis, and extraordinary vnion very praegnant are thoſe notable paradoxes of <hi>Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alphonſ: Thoſtat: Abulenſis <hi>in his</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes.</note> as he termes them; as that <hi>Chriſt is a Lyon which was ſeene, and which was not ſeene;</hi> which was heard, and which was not heard; which was knowne, and which was not knowne: as that he was <hi>a lambe vberatus, &amp; non vberatus,</hi> that was ſhorne, and yet came not before the ſhearer: that bleated and yet did not open his mouth, that dyed, and yet did not dye: As that he was <hi>a Serpent and an Eagle,</hi> that ſaw and did not ſee,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14296:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> that heard, and did not heare; that mooued, and did not mooue; that came againe to the place, from which they neuer went; that reſted, and yet did not reſt, that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and yet were not renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that reioyced, and yet did not reioyce: for looke what hee did as man, the ſame hee did not as God.</p>
            <p>But I haue ſtrayed ſomewhat from my text,<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the third gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</note> and haue ſoared with the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle into heauen to ſeeke Chriſt there, whom <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſhewes me vpon earth here: <hi>Behold the man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold,</hi> I ſay, and <hi>behold</hi> him <hi>vnder two formes.</hi> Firſt <hi>in his owne ſhape:</hi> then <hi>in thine owne.</hi> In his owne behold his <hi>Maieſty:</hi> In thine owne his <hi>miſerie.</hi> In his <hi>Maieſty</hi> behold the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">Inſtit: de iur. Nat. Gent. &amp; ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil. § Sed ius.</note> Not <hi>a man but the man.</hi> When I ſay the lawes of <hi>Solon</hi> or <hi>Draco</hi> (ſaid the moſt ſacred <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian</hi>) thinke then I ſay the ciuill law of the Athenians: but if I ſay the <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill law</hi> &amp; ad no name of any nation,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14296:13"/> thinke then I ſay, the ciuill lawe of the Romans; as when we ſay <hi>the Poet,</hi> and adde no name <hi>Subanditur apud Graecos egregius</hi> Homerus, <hi>apud nos</hi> Virgilius. I alter him on litle, &amp; apply it to my text; When I ſay the lawes of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> it is a cleare caſe I ſay the ciuill lawe of the Romans: but if I ſay <hi>the lawe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thorah. Hieron: in prologo ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lealo. Deutr. <hi>4.8.</hi>
               </note> and adde no name, know then I ſay <hi>the lawe</hi> of God. For <hi>what Nation</hi> is ſo great (ſaith your Lord) that hath ordinances and <hi>lawes</hi> ſo righteous, as all <hi>this lawe</hi> which I ſet before you this day? So likewiſe when I ſay <hi>Eſaias</hi> the Prophet, or <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> the man of God, it is plaine, I ſay <hi>Eſai,</hi> or <hi>Eli:</hi> But if I ſay<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>the prophet,</hi> or he that<note n="b" place="margin">Shiloh. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.10.</note> 
               <hi>is to come,</hi> or<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.5.</note> the <hi>man,</hi> and adde no name, knowe then I ſay Chriſt. For ſuch an emphaſis oft times and ſtrength of ſignification doth the Greeke article import, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as<note n="d" place="margin">Epiphan. in panar: libr. <hi>1.</hi> Tom. <hi>1.</hi> contr: Samarit: Haer. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> obſerues; and that it ſo doth in this place the Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke interpretation doth well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14296:13"/> 
               <hi>Ho gabhro.</hi> Behold the man;<note place="margin">Metaphr: Syriac. Diog: La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert: <hi>in</hi> Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes <hi>the Cynicke.</hi>
               </note> not <hi>a man,</hi> but <hi>the man.</hi> Not ſuch a man, as the Philoſopher would not ſee, when he ſaid <hi>I would ſee men,</hi> and not <hi>Pigmees;</hi> nor ſuch a man as hee ſaw againe, and would not ſpeake with, ſaying,<note place="margin">O verè phrygiae ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Hom: virg.</note> I would ſpeake with <hi>Men,</hi> and not with <hi>Beaſtes;</hi> nor ſuch a man, as a Captaine ſaide he ſaw many, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and no men,</hi> but ſuch a man, as there are not many ſuch: <hi>Homo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paucorum hominum:</hi> nay ſuch a one as beſides himſelfe, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any ſuch; <hi>Verè vir,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. Tuſc. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> as from whome all virtue deriueth her name: a worthy man, an excellent man, not ſuch a man amongſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand:
<q>
                  <l>Quem ſeſe ore ferens?<note place="margin">Virg: AEneid. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> quam forti pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore et armis?</l>
                  <l>Crede equidem (nec vana fides) genus eſſe deorum.</l>
                  <l>Degeneres animos timor arguit. —</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But thou arte beautifull <hi>my loue</hi> as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14296:14"/> 
               <hi>Tirzah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Salomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of Chriſt, as vnited, and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with his Church <hi>Cant.</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: <hi>Dan:</hi> 7. and 10. <hi>Apoc:</hi> 1. &amp; 19. <hi>Ch. Vultum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Ludolph: in prologo de vita Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</hi>
               </note> comely as Hieruſalem, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as an armie of banners: <hi>Thine head</hi> is an head of many crownes of gold, thy buſh purple, thy lockes curled: <hi>Thy haire</hi> of thine head like a flocke of goates looking downe from <hi>Gilead: Thy temples</hi> within thy lockes as a peece of a Pomegranate: <hi>Thy face</hi> as the lightning, ſhining as the Sunne ſhineth in his ſtrength: <hi>Thy noſe</hi> as <hi>Lebanon,</hi> thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance excellent as the <hi>Cedars; Thine eyes</hi> as the Doues; O turne awaye thine eyes from mee, for they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome mee; Thou haſt waſhed them with milke in the Riuers of Heſhbon: <hi>Thy cheekes</hi> as the Roſe, as a bedde of Spices, and ſweete flowers: <hi>Thy lippes</hi> as the Lillies, as a thred of Scarlet, dropping Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: <hi>Thy mouth</hi> as ſweete things; O kiſſe mee with the kiſſes of thy mouth, thy loue is ſweeter then Wine; Hony, and Milke are vnder
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14296:14"/> thy tongue: <hi>Thy teeth</hi> like a flocke of ſheepe going vp from waſhing: <hi>Thy necke</hi> as the Tower of <hi>Dauid,</hi> a thouſand Shieldes, and Targets hang thereon: <hi>Thy bodie</hi> like a Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolite, and <hi>thy ſtature</hi> as a Palme tree: <hi>Thy breaſtes</hi> as two young roes on the Mountaines of Bether: <hi>Thy bellie</hi> like White Iuory couered with Saphites: <hi>Thy nauell</hi> as a round Cuppe full of Grace, and running ouer: <hi>Thy loynes</hi> are girt about with a girdle of Golde, of the Golde of Vphaz: I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared thee ô my loue to the troupe of Horſes in the charets of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh: Thine armes</hi> like poliſhed braſſe thrice purified in the Furnace; thine <hi>handes</hi> as the ringes of Golde ſet about with Tharſhiſh: On <hi>thy thigh</hi> a name enwritten, <hi>the King of Kinges and Lorde of Lordes,</hi> and the <hi>Ioyntes</hi> of thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14296:15"/> thighes as Iewels: <hi>Thy legges</hi> as Pillars of Marble ſet vpon ſockets of pure Gold:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 52. <hi>Nahum.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>thy feete,</hi> O how beautifull are the goings of the feete of thee, that bringeſt glad tidings of peace? <hi>Thy whole Chriſt</hi> annointed with oyle of gladneſſe aboue thy fellowes: <hi>All thy garments</hi> of fleſh, redolent with <hi>Myrrhe, Aloes,</hi> and Caſſia out of the Iuory Pallaces: whiles the King is at his repaſt, my ſpiknard giues the ſmell thereof: <hi>my whole welbeloued</hi> is as a bundle of <hi>Myrrhe</hi> vnto me, as a cluſter of Camphire in the vines of Engedi.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Quem non, vt caetera deſint,</l>
               <l>Forma mouere poteſt? certè mea pectora mouit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>O that thou</hi> wert as my brother, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the breaſts of my mother,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant:</hi> 8.1.1.12.</note> that I might finde thee within, and kiſſe thee with the lippes of deuotion, and embrace thee with the armes of loue: thou ſhouldeſt lie betweene my breaſts.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14296:15"/>
            <p>I might ſeeme here much to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt your wiſdomes, if I miſdoubted at all, leſt in this deſcription of Chriſt you might miſtake my meaning, and take him in ſuch materiall ſorte, as the wordes doe ſound: But I ſpeake vnto you that haue a more ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vnderſtanding, and that can iudge of more then I can ſay. Onely this I ſay, and it ſtandes with good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to, and the Scriptures of God doe not gaineſay; but that the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of Chriſt white, and ruddie.</hi> Cant <hi>5.10.</hi> Fronte ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens cum facie ſine ruga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſine macula; quamrubor moderatus venusta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit ex A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nnal: Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Ludolph: in prologo de vita Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</note> 
               <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion</hi> of this man might be all <hi>white and well-coloured,</hi> as being of a more tender and delicate fleſh then we are: but that the ſymmetrie and lineaments of his body might be of a more better and aequall proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as it is written; he encreaſed <hi>in wiſedome, and ſtature and grace,</hi> and fauour with God, and man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 2.52.</note> 
               <hi>Gratior et gratioſior</hi> as <hi>Zanchie</hi> notes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch:</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place.</note> But it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other beauty that I now ſpeake of, and aboue all the beauty of the Kings
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14296:16"/> ſonne is all glorious within: within, I ſaye, there within are thoſe moſt peereleſſe, and matchleſſe virtues and beauties, which neuer yet, nor <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor <hi>Daniel,</hi> nor <hi>Salomon,</hi> nor <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> nor any tongues of men, nor Angelles coulde ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently adumbrate, or expreſſe. Returne then,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant:</hi> 6.12.3.11.</note> returne O <hi>Shula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite</hi> returne: returne I ſaye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and behoulde my <hi>wellbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> behoulde <hi>my Louer</hi> (O Daughters of Hieruſalem.) This is that King <hi>Salomon</hi> with his Crowne, wherewith his mother Crowned him in the daye of his marriage, euen in the day of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d diuiſion of the third generall circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance the ſecond diſtinction.</note>
               <hi>Hitherto</hi> haue you beheld (deere Chriſtian brethren) and more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after you may beholde this moſt worthy man, of what Maieſty and Excellencie hee was in himſelfe: Meane while beholde a little of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14296:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> what <hi>Miſery and Vility</hi> hee is in thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Diog. Laert: <hi>in</hi> Diogenes <hi>the</hi> Cynick.</note> 
               <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> reportes of <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Cynicke,</hi> that hee taxed ſometimes, (and in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite verye prettylie to) certayne vaine gloryous Sophiſters, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that wiſedome conſiſted in words; and hee taxed them vnder this ſtile, that they were thriſe men, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Thriſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> for <hi>thriſe-miſerable:</hi> if euer any one man were thriſe a man, that is thriſe miſerable, poore Ieſus was that man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezechias</hi> as it is ſtoryed in <hi>the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> of Chronicles,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron:</hi> 29 5.16.</note> when the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lorde was prophaned by certayne wicked perſons, hee commaunded that firſt the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> ſhoulde bee <hi>purified,</hi> and that then the filth thereof ſhoulde bee conueyed into the Ryuer Cedron. We were (beloued) that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and liuelye Temple propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Diuels, poſſeſſed by euill
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14296:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpirits, euen our owne infinite euils, and diueliſh ſinnes: Chriſt was that cleere riuer <hi>Cedron,</hi> ſuſtaining the beautie of heauen with his ſtreames: Into this heauenly <hi>Cedron</hi> then were all the pollutions of our earthly man caſt. Chriſt was the Prieſt that purged vs: the font and baſon that dipped vs: the water and Hyſop that waſhed vs: the pure fine linnen towell receauing the filth of our feet into it owne ſelfe, and wiping vs cleane; In ſo much that now we are ſtrong, and he is weake: we are cleane, and he is foule: we are white and rud-colloured, and he hath neither forme nor beautie: we acquitted from ſinne, and he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned for ſinne: we bleſſed, and he curſed: we repriued, and himſelfe hanged on the tree: we were all this for him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 53.4 <hi>Matt:</hi> 8.17 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24, &amp;c.</note> and he was all that for vs. <hi>Verè languores noſtros ipſe tulit.</hi> But of his paſſion anon: Inſomuch that the Church her-ſelfe ſtands amazed at this ſo ſuddaine &amp; ſtrange alteration;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14296:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> and therfore as if he had <hi>bene growne</hi> out of knowledge, ſhe demaunds this quaeſtion; <hi>Who is this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 63.1 <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.13</note> 
               <hi>who is this that commeth from Edom,</hi> with redde gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from <hi>Bezrah?</hi> wherefore doeſt thou (O Lord) weare garments all be ſpotted, and died with blood, like vnto them that ſtampe Grapes in the Wine preſſe? this is very ſtrange (me thinkes) to ſee the ſonne of God in the ſhape of a ſinner, the God of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie apparelled with ignominy, life her ſelfe put to death.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 28.21.</note>—<hi>Heu quantum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus ab illo Hectore? His workes</hi> (as <hi>Eſay</hi> had good reaſon to ſay) <hi>are very</hi> ſtrange, and farre vnlike himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> this much I thought good to declare vnto you,<note place="margin">The third diuiſion of the third generall circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</note> as touching the man, firſt in his owne perſon, then in our owne; Each of them by way of expoſition; <hi>vt hominem ſcias,</hi> that we might know him to be a man. Now againe by way of exhortation, <hi>Behold the man.</hi> And that the eye of our faith may haue ſome certaine obiect, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14296:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> to fixe and ſetle it ſelfe; Behold him firſt <hi>in his life and actions;</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in his <hi>death and paſſion;</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>his ſeſſion</hi> at the right hand of God his father, &amp; <hi>interceſſion.</hi> In the actions of his life behold him with a zealous, yet <hi>ſober eye</hi> of <hi>imitation;</hi> In his death and paſſion, behold him with the eye of <hi>Sympathie and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> In his ſeſſion, and interceſſion, beholde him with the eye of <hi>affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> and <hi>conſolation.</hi> Firſt in his life and actions:<note n="a" place="margin">Omnis Chriſti Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The actions</hi> of Chriſt (ſay the Fathers in generall) are a Chriſtians imitations:<note n="*" place="margin">August:</note> 
               <hi>The ſumme of Chriſtian</hi> Religion (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>) is to <hi>imitate</hi> Chriſt: Chriſt himſelfe I inſcribe<note n="c" place="margin">A Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Glaſſe for a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſt. W: Th: <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph de vita Ieſu Chriſti. part:</hi> 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>A Kenning-Glaſſe for a Chriſtian; Speculum vitae Chriſtianae.</hi> A warrant of this inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I haue, firſt out of Gods owne mouth;<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.9.40. <hi>Acts.</hi> 7.44. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Matth:</hi> 17.5. <hi>Matt:</hi> 11.29. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 13 15. <hi>Hebr:</hi> 12.1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Inſpice et fac: See, looke,</hi> and do according to the <hi>mirrour</hi> I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee in the mount: Behold this is my welbeloued ſonne, in whom I am
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14296:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> well pleaſed, <hi>Hunc audite,</hi> heare him. Secondly of Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Diſcite a me,</hi> looke vpon mee, learne of mee: <hi>I haue</hi> giuen you (ſaith he) an example. Thirdly the Apoſtles all exhort; <hi>Aſpicite,</hi> looke, conſider Chriſt, how he endured the Croſſe: runne with patience the race, which is ſet afore you: <hi>Looke vpon Ieſus</hi> the author and finiſher of your faith. Art thou then (O man of God) affected zealouſlie to be a <hi>Chriſtian indeed?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt: de vitae Chriſtiana. Bernard in his Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> no longer to vſurpe the name of a Chriſtian? Loe heere then a <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Glaſſe</hi> to thy hand; Behold this man; marke well the face of his life; compare, and compoſe the countenance of thy conuerſation accordingly. Art thou then (for example and inſtance) art thou ambitious, and proude? pomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? inſolent? of much attendance? Looke vpon him, and wonder at thy ſelfe <hi>Rex fieri noluit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt:</note> Hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to bee a King, or his whole
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14296:19"/> traine and retinue was one poore man, and a weake woman, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary,—ijdem parentquè iubentque.</hi> Haſt thou with Lucifer ſaid in thine hart? <hi>I will aſcend</hi> into <hi>heauen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 14.13.</note> and exalt my throne aboue the ſtarres of God: I will enthronize my ſelfe vpon the mount of the congregation in the ſides of the North: I will be like the moſt high. Looke vpon him and wonder at thy ſelfe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 88.3.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoule</hi> (ſaith he) drawes neere vnto hell: I am in the midſt of you, as the meaneſt of you:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 22.6.</note> a <hi>man and no God: a worme</hi> and no man:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 131.1.2.</note> mine <hi>hart</hi> not haughtie: mine eyes not loftie: I am in my ſelfe as a wayned childe: Lord who is like vnto thee? Haſt thou with Anti-chriſt, and Atheiſts, and many falſe Chriſtes aduanced thy ſelfe an <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary againſt all that is God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 2.4.</note> Haſt thou ſate as God, in the temple of God, vaunting thy ſelfe that thou wert God?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.6.7.</note> Looke vpon him and wonder at thy ſelfe: <hi>he, when he was in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14296:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> the forme of</hi> God, aequall with God, humbled himſelfe in the habite of man vnto the death, euen the death, of the Croſſe: Gaue <hi>vnto Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth:</hi> 22.21. <hi>On Iob.</hi> 41. <hi>Greg. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral:</hi> 34.21.</note> that which was <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and <hi>vnto God</hi> that which was Gods, and this he did, <hi>Vt ſuperbum non eſſe hominem doceret hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milis Deus.</hi> Art thou auaritious and couetous? <hi>ioyning houſe</hi> to houſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 5.8.</note> and land to land? ſtill <hi>gaping</hi> after Gold,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 31.8.</note> and heaping vp money &amp; treaſures? Looke vpon him: <hi>Pauper eſſe voluit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt:</note> he would needs be a poore man: he neither had, nor would haue any ſuch thing: nor ſiluer, nor gold: nor houſe, nor land:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math:</hi> 8.20</note> not an hole to hide his head in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Godlineſſe was vnto him great riches. Art thou luxurious, and lecherous? a glutton? a drunkard? feaſting and feeding thy ſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare? ouercome by thy body?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud:</hi> 12.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 47.19.</note> and bowing thy loynes vnto wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? Looke vpon him: his hunger, <hi>Math: 4:</hi> his thirſt, <hi>Iohn 4: his onely meate, and drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.34.</note> to doe the will of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14296:20"/> his father which is in heauen: his Father knew no woman: his Mother was a Virgin: himſelfe abhorred ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of man.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 41.10.11.</note> Art thou as the <hi>Leuiathan</hi> in <hi>Iob?</hi> thy mouth as fire, thy noſtrils as the ſmoake? in ire? in enuie? reuenging thine enemies? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pining at thy friends? ſtill breathing out threatnings, and ſlaughters? Looke vpon him, and wonder at thy ſelfe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 53.7</note> 
               <hi>As a Lambe</hi> before the ſhearer, he opened not his mouth; he enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed none:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math:</hi> 5.22</note> pittied all he <hi>that is angrie with his brother</hi> (ſaith he) is culpable of Iudgement.</p>
            <p>In fine, art thou deuoted to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 6.4.</note> ſet vpon ſlouth? lying vpon <hi>Beds of Iuorie?</hi> and ſtretching thy ſelfe vpon thy bed? Looke vpon him and wonder at thy ſelfe: hee walked the world ouer: from cittie to cittie: from one region to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: he preached: he prayed: he iourneyed, and was wearie in his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14296:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> iourneyes: I will ſay all at once,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>W: Th:</hi> de Camp: De Regia via Sancta crucis.</note> 
               <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta vita Chriſti crux eſt;</hi> and inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent it were, that vnder Chriſt our head of thornes we Chriſtians ſhould pamper ſo delicate bodyes. Thou ſeeſt now (good Chriſtian) I am ſure, with how manye foule and ougly ſpottes of mortall ſinne thy ſoule is ſtained. <hi>The office and</hi> end of a <hi>Kenning-glaſse</hi> (thou maiſt well conceiue) conſiſtes not ſo much in Kenning the deformities of the face, as in correcting them. Hee that fanſifieth himſelfe cured with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a <hi>Phyſician</hi> talke onely, is like one of thoſe idle hearers, whome Saint <hi>Iames</hi> admoniſhed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1:22.</note> that they ſhoulde be <hi>Doers alſo,</hi> and not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers onelye, deceauing themſelues: and he that imagineth hee hath done away the ſpirituall ſpottes of his face with behoulding them in this <hi>loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glaſſe</hi> onelye, is like that man in Saint <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1.23.24.</note> that behelde his <hi>naturall face in a Glaſſe,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14296:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſidered himſelfe, &amp; went his way, and forgot immediately,<note place="margin">Dion: Carth. in Speculo Amatorum mundi.</note> what one he was: <hi>non ſic impij, non ſic itur ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra:</hi> away, away with ſuch vaine ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations: examine rather the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aright:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 1:25.</note> 
               <hi>looke well in</hi> this perfect law of liberty: runne from Chriſt to thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.14.</note> and againe from thy ſelfe to Chriſt: <hi>Waſhe thee:</hi> make thee cleane: <hi>Waſh white</hi> thy ſtole, nay thy ſoule &amp; body in the blood of the Lambe.<note place="margin">Greg:</note> 
               <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culaſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory) in quibus animae ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctae ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per aſpiciunt.</hi> The face of Chriſt <hi>is a glaſſe</hi> which the Saints of God do view, and reuiew, that when ought in themſelues is amiſſe, they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it. Compare then the pride thou ſeeſt in thine owne face with Chriſtes humility: thy couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with his contentednes: thy lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, and prodigality in meates and drinkes with his parſimony, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie: thine anger with his amiable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: thine enuy with his innocence: thy lazineſſe, with his labours: thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14296:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> with his virtues: compare them I ſay, and conforme thee: that in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to that vayle one <hi>Moſes</hi> face thou maiſt alſo ſay,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18</note> I ſee <hi>in a glaſſe the glory</hi> of God with open face, and am <hi>conformed and transformed into the ſame image</hi> from glory to glory.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt:</note> 
               <hi>Etenim ad hoc vtile eſt nobis</hi> ſpeculum, <hi>et facilem facit tranſpoſitionem</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this notwithſtanding ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Anthropolatrae</hi> there are (as the <hi>Emperour in his Code</hi> recordes of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius</hi>) that commit Idolatry with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">C. de Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Trinit: Nos re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. C. de Haeret: &amp; Manich damnato. Qui cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</note> that <hi>make mirrours</hi> of <hi>men:</hi> ſome of themſelues, and ſome of others. Of themſelues; ſuch are they, that <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſsus</hi> like are in loue with themſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Actes.</hi> 36.37. <hi>Origen</hi> in his firſt booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. Ioſeph:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: 20.2 <hi>Euſeb.</hi> 2.14</note> 
               <hi>Theudas amongst the Iews, Iudas</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the <hi>Galilaeans, Doſitheus</hi> amongſt the <hi>Samarians,</hi> each of them profeſſing himſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome miraculous man at leaſt, and the laſt perſwading himſelfe to be Chriſt: ſuch was <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Demetrius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Mach.</hi> 10 72.</note> 
               <hi>go aske</hi> (ſaide he to <hi>Ionathas</hi>) and learne who
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14296:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> I am. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Quam pulchru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> est digito monſtrari, &amp; dicier hic eſt?</hi> &amp; ſuch a one I ſuppoſe he was, ſtrouting vp and downe, &amp; gazing on himſelfe; <hi>Is not this great</hi> Babel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.27.</note> that I haue built for the houſe of my kingdome, and for the honour of my maieſtie? ſuch and ſuch like men are as <hi>thoſe glaſſes of</hi> wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 3.23</note> by which the daughters of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on decked themſelues, fraile, &amp; fickle. Would God our Ladies of England, after the example of thoſe auncient <hi>matrons of Iſraell,</hi> could be content to correct their <hi>Glaſſes</hi> by <hi>Chriſt our Glaſſe,</hi> and to conſecrate them to <hi>the making of the Lauer of Gods</hi> Tabernacle.<note place="margin">Exod: <hi>38.8</hi> Onkelus. &amp; Kimchi. Matthias I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llyricus.</note> Some others make others <hi>Glaſſes</hi> to them ſelues, they commit (as I ſaide) Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie with men: ſuch a wicked Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe was that wretched woman of Samaria,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.12.</note> ſaying vnto Chriſt; <hi>art thou greater</hi> then our father <hi>Iacob?</hi> Such were the Iewes;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.53.</note> art <hi>thou greater</hi> then our father <hi>Abraham?</hi> whom makeſt thou thy ſelfe? Such were ſome of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14296:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Phariſies; <hi>be thou his diſciple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9.28.</note> the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt, if thou wilt, as for vs, <hi>we are Moſes diſciples:</hi> And I <hi>am of Paule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1:12.</note> I am of <hi>Apollos,</hi> I am of <hi>Cephas:</hi> I am of the rule of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> I am of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>S. Dominick,</hi> the Canons of their liues muſt be the rules for mine:—<hi>O i. mitatores ſtultum pecus.</hi> Good Chriſt what is it not <hi>thou that haſt the</hi> wordes of aeternall life abiding with thee?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.68.</note> then whither doe wee runne from thee? Is it not <hi>thou</hi> that art <hi>the way?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6.</note> Then why do we not walke in thee? Is it not thou that art <hi>the trueth?</hi> then why do we not beleeue in thee? Is it not thou that art <hi>the life?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambr:</note> then why do we not liue in thee. <hi>Omnia habemus in Christo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) and Chriſt is all in all vnto vs. If thou feare death, he is life: if thou flie darkeneſſe, he is light: if thou affect heauen, he is the way: he is the way inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the truth infallible, the life euerlaſting. And neyther yet doe I condemne here any due aeſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or <hi>Imitation of Saints,</hi> Nay I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14296:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> commend it rather, and charge you to;<note n="a" place="margin">The ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Saints. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Chryſoſt: Ludolph: de vita Chriſti part:</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 66</note> 
               <hi>Imitamini fidem ducum veſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> Imitate the Saints of God. <hi>Speculum eſt, &amp; ſpirituale,</hi> So many Saints (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) ſo many Seeing-Glaſſes hath a Chriſtian:<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 51.2.</note> conſider <hi>Abraham your</hi> father, and <hi>Sarah</hi> that bare you:<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12.</note> walke <hi>in the</hi> ſteps of their faith:<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames.</hi> 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>Take</hi> (my brethren) <hi>the Prophets for an enſample:</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. <hi>Mach:</hi> 2.51.</note> 
               <hi>Call to remembrance</hi> (my ſonnes) <hi>what actes</hi> our Fathers did in their times, ſo ſhall yee receiue great honor, and an euerlaſting name: you haue read <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>long patience</hi> of <hi>Iob,</hi> and haue heard what end the Lord made. The way (ſome ſay) <hi>to prouoke Elephants to fight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Math:</hi> 6.34.</note> is to ſhew them the bloud of Grapes, and Mulberies: The blood of ſo many Saints, of Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſors, Virgins, Men, Women, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what recreant would it not whet vnto battaile?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corinth:</hi> 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce factiſumus ſpectacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum</hi> (ſaith one of the Apoſtles in the name of all) we are made as ſo many
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14296:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>ſpectacles, and gazing</hi> ſtockes vnto the world, and to the Angels, and to men.<note place="margin">Th: a Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pis de exemplis Sanctorum patrum. Terent: in Adelph.</note> 
               <hi>Intuere ſanctorum,</hi> and ſo foorth. See, (ſaith another) <hi>the examples</hi> of the Saints: <hi>Deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inſpicere tanquam in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum vitas hominum iubeo.</hi> And this to what end? or why were theſe things then related of them?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.23. <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 15.4.</note> or why doe I now repeate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you? Surely <hi>not for them but for vs,</hi> that we alſo through patience,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt: Greg: Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Saint Michael, &amp; <hi>all Angels all Saints day.</hi>
               </note> and conſolation of the Scriptures might haue hope, and ſo directing our liues <hi>according to their good enſamples,</hi> may finally attaine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thoſe Palmes, and crownes of life, for which they combatted vnto death. Imitate then on Gods name the Saints of God, but this muſt thou do,<note place="margin">A limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Imitation of Saints. <hi>Th: Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas on the</hi> 15. <hi>of the Romanes.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11:1 <hi>Auguſt: in pſ:</hi> 39. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not at all times, nor in all things: imitate me</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paule) as I</hi> imitate Chriſt, ſo far &amp; no farther. For doth he not imitate Chriſt, he ers himſelfe, <hi>Iſte in ecleſia ordo eſt,</hi> this (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) is the inſtitution of the Church: <hi>virtutes imitamur, non vitia.</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14296:24"/> To particularize a while. Thou maieſt imitate now the obedience of <hi>Abraham,</hi> thou maieſt not his ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: that was then commendable in him, that were now damnable in thee. Thou maieſt imitate the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundneſſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the eloquence of <hi>Aaron;</hi> thou maieſt not their incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie: thou maieſt imitate the ardent faith, and zeale of <hi>Dauid,</hi> thou maieſt not his adulterie, and murther: thou maieſt the profeſſion of <hi>Peter,</hi> thou maieſt not his deniall with an oath: Thou maiſt the patience of <hi>Paul,</hi> thou maieſt not his perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: thou mayeſt the amiable qualities of the other Apoſtles, thou mayeſt not their ambition: In ſhort the Saints of God are <hi>Seeing-Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> I ſay, and men may ſee ſome thing in them but it is but <hi>in part</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainely,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>as through a Glaſſe obſcurely:</hi> there are in their ſeuerall legends and liues certaine beauties (I grant) and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14296:24"/> ſplendors of life, but they are but here and there, and there are ſpots too.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>Kenning-Glaſſe</hi> of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that I commend, the one A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalyſis alone of Chriſt his life,<note place="margin">In ſplendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp;c. pſ: <hi>110.3.</hi> vviſd. <hi>7.26</hi> Hebr: <hi>1:3.</hi> Coloſſ <hi>1.15.</hi>
               </note> is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely perfect in it ſelfe, pure, cleare, ſpotleſſe, <hi>the ſplendour of Saints, the luſtre</hi> of the euerlaſting light, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled <hi>mirrour</hi> of the maieſtie of God the influence of the Almightie, and <hi>Image of</hi> his goodneſſe. Good Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> compares this <hi>Mirrour of Man-kinde</hi> vnto that <hi>faſcicle, or flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Myrrhe</hi> amiddeſt the breaſts of the ſpouſe,<note place="margin">Cant. <hi>1.12.</hi> Bern: in Cant. Serm. <hi>43.</hi> Serm: <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> and intertexeth his compariſon thus: Here is a flower and a <hi>Glaſſe, Flos virginitas, flos martyrium, flos actio bona,</hi> A Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Chamber, A Flower of the Garden, A Flower of the Field: Hee is a Flower of the Chamber, <hi>Speculum et exemplum,</hi> An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and <hi>Glaſſe</hi> of all bountye,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14296:25"/> and goodneſſe; he is a flower of the garden, <hi>Virgo virga virgine generatus,</hi> euen Ieſus of <hi>Nazereth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Netzar. Iſaiah.</hi> 11.1</note> 
               <hi>the flower</hi> of <hi>Ieſſe:</hi> he is a flower of the field, a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, the crowne of Martyrs, the forme of Martyrs. <hi>Vtrunque (imo omnia) es mihi domine Ieſu, et</hi> ſpeculum <hi>patiendi et praemium patientis.</hi> Here maieſt thou reade at once the Innocence of <hi>Abel,</hi> the righteouſneſſe of <hi>Noah,</hi> the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the chaſtitie of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> the mildeneſſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence of <hi>Phinees,</hi> the ſtrength of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> the wiſdome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the diet of <hi>Daniel,</hi> the patience of <hi>Iob,</hi> the pietie of <hi>Tobie,</hi> the humilitie of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>Mary:</hi> hee was truly faythfull in heart without fayning: humble without hypocriſie: ſober without ſowerneſſe: wife as a Serpent: innocent as a Doue: ſtout as a Lion: meeke as a Lambe: what ſhall I more ſay? Here maieſt thou haue all that which all they haue, and here maieſt thou haue that, which all
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14296:25"/> they put them all together, and they had it not. If any man require more in ſpeciall to reade of this argument, I reporte him to <hi>Ludolphus</hi> of the life of Ieſus Chriſt, to <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Campis</hi> of the imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, or rather with <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> to the foure Euangeliſtes.<note place="margin">Auguſt: Ludolph: in prologo.</note> For that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſaith he) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informe vs of the life, &amp; manners of Chriſt, as the Goſpell of Chriſt. I for my part muſt on with my text, and paſſe ouer in a word, which eftſoones I propoſed, namely <hi>a ſobrietie in the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of Chriſt.</hi> As we are zealous, ſo muſt we be ſober: As therefore in the imitation of Saints, thou maieſt imitate them (I ſaid) but that nor at all times, nor in all things: ſo, and much more ſo, we may, nay we muſt, imitate<note n="a" place="margin">A limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the imitation of Chriſt.</note> Chriſt, &amp; that at all times, but not <hi>in all things.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">De conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat:d ſt. <hi>2.</hi> Liquido ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paret in Gloſſa.</note> 
               <hi>Non omnis Chriſti actio noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra eſt lectio.</hi> Euery action of Chriſt is not an imitation for a Chriſtian.<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt: S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</note> 
               <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatores Chriſti eſſe debemus,</hi> we muſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate Chriſt, but we muſt imitate him
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14296:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> in his mercies,<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles.</note> we may not in his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: we may not as <hi>Bladud a</hi> Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Prince and founder of the hotte Bathes (as they ſay) make vs waxen wings, and flie in the winde, vnleſſe we will breake our neckes, as he did; yet Chriſt <hi>flyeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>and commeth flying</hi> on the wings of the winde: we may not take vpon vs to rayſe the dead, to turne water into Wine, as prophane <hi>Necromancers,</hi> and iuglers doe, yet Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Exi Lazare,</hi> come foorth <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 11.43 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.7.8.</note> and <hi>tranſubſtantiated water</hi> into Wine in Canah of Galilee: wee may not goe about as the <hi>God of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighe did,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn Wier <hi>de ietuniis Comment.</hi> The Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> legend.</note> as Saint <hi>Mary</hi> the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt, to walke on the waues, to tread the pathes of the ſea, to do all, that Chriſt could do, as God. For moſt true it is in this, which in another ſenſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 8.21.</note> 
               <hi>whither I goe</hi> (ſayd Ieſus to the Iewes) thither you cannot come; and Chriſt vnto <hi>Peter, whither I goe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn:</hi> 13.36</note> thou canſt not followe me.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles:</hi> 2:12.</note> 
               <hi>Quid eſt enim homo vt ſequi poſsit
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14296:26"/> regem factore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt: de verbis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini: Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt: in Pſ: <hi>90.</hi>
               </note> as it is in the vulgar Latine tranſlation. He ſaith not (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) thou canſt not be my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, thou canſt not follow me, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou create a new world,</hi> or walke on the ſeas, or make the blinde to ſee, the halt to go, the deafe to heare, the dead to ryſe againe. For theſe are my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles <hi>vnimitable</hi> for vs, and as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in that reply of Chriſt to <hi>Saint Iohns</hi> diſciples,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math:</hi> 11.4.5. <hi>Luc:</hi> 7:22.23.</note> he reſerues them as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to himſelfe. <hi>Quid ergo eſt?</hi> what it is then that the <hi>eye of</hi> thine <hi>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> muſt aime at in Chriſt? Chriſt tels thee himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math:</hi> 11.29:</note> 
               <hi>diſcite a me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quia mitis ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> learne of me for I am hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; meeke be ye, as I am: <hi>be yee holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit:</hi> 11.44. 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.3.6.</note> for I am holy: <hi>walke as I haue</hi> walked: <hi>keepe my</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements: <hi>loue one</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: hereby ſhal al men know,<note place="margin">Iohn: <hi>13.34.35.</hi> Auguſt. <hi>on the 90.</hi> Pſalm. Theodor: de virt: Act.</note> that ye are my diſciples. <hi>Quod factus eſt propter te, hoc in Chriſto debes atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere, vt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris eum:</hi> Loue and hate that, which Chriſt loued, and hated, as hee was God, and thou dooſt imitate Chriſt, as much as a man may
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14296:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> imitate God: do that which Chriſt did, as he was man, and thou doſt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Chriſt, as a Chriſtian ought. <hi>Magnus eſſe vis?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt de verbis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> 
               <hi>a minimo incipe? am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula per hominem, et peruenies ad Deum.</hi> To knit vp this point, what bleſſed <hi>Bernards</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceite was of his faſcicle of Myrrhe, the ſame is mine of this <hi>my glaſſe,</hi> this was that <hi>mirrour of man,</hi> which the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> carried in her wombe, the ſpouſe betweene her breaſts, <hi>Simeon</hi> in his armes, <hi>Zachary</hi> in his hand, <hi>Iohn</hi> in his boſome, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> dalied with on his knees.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor:</hi> 4:10</note> O that all we, that are Chriſtians, would do the like,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezeche.</hi> 9.6 <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.17 <hi>Bern: in Cant: Serm:</hi> 21.</note> that we would <hi>manifeſt in</hi> our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies the life of Ieſus: that wee would <hi>marke our foreheads with the marke</hi> of Chriſt: that we would erect <hi>his image</hi> in our harts <hi>aut naſentis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">O ſi Ieſus Crucifixus in Cor noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. <hi>W. Th.</hi> a Camp: De Imit: Chriſti. L. <hi>1.</hi> C. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>aut lacte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis, aut docentis,</hi> euen from his cradle to the croſſe: that we would alwaies contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate this <hi>Kenning-glaſse, Christ, and his croſſe:</hi> that we would carry him in our boſome, and lay him amidſt our
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14296:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> breaſts,<note place="margin">Bernard in Cant: Serm: <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> and haue him alwayes afore our eyes, <hi>non retro in humeris, ſed ante prae oculis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly I exhort;<note place="margin">The third diuiſion of the third generall circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance the ſecond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction. <hi>Innocent. de ſacro Altaris myſterio. Libr.</hi> 5. <hi>C:</hi> 9 <hi>Math.</hi> 26.28. <hi>Marck.</hi> 14.33.34.</note> Behold the man in his death &amp; paſſion. They that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the paſſion of Chriſt digeſt it vſually into a <hi>triple paſsion:</hi> the firſt they terme his <hi>propaſsion</hi> the ſecond, and that moſt properly, his <hi>paſsion,</hi> the third his <hi>compaſsion:</hi> his propaſſion was in his ſoule, his paſſion in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his compaſſion in his harte. Of his <hi>propaſsion</hi> he proteſteth himſelfe; <hi>My ſoule</hi> is very heauy, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death: Of his <hi>compaſsion</hi> he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for them that crucified him, <hi>Father forgiue</hi> them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.24.</note> they know not what they doe: Of his <hi>paſsion</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes; O <hi>vos omnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thron: <hi>1:12.</hi> O homo vide, quae pro te patior. Bernard.</note> Oh all yee that paſſe by the way, behold and ſee, if euer any <hi>paſsion</hi> were like this of mine? Of this paſſion I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate. And here I ſhall requeſt all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> to lift vp the <hi>eyes</hi> of their <hi>compaſsion</hi> yet a little high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14296:28"/> and to beholde the man. Come forth ô yee daughters of <hi>Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3:11.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde your King, Brethren if wee bee men (except we be Iewes or Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens) behold we the man; Which the ſunne for our ſinnes was aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to beholde; the Daughters of Hieruſalem wept out their eyes to beholde; the dead corpſes in the graues reſumed their eyes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. Behold I ſay (O Chriſtian ſoule) behold and ſay <hi>Quis ego, et quis tu Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine?</hi> Who art thou, and who am I O Lorde? O what hart doth not riue and rent in ſunder? What hardneſſe is not mollified? What eyes doe not ſtreame with teares beholding ſuch a lamentable and dolefull ſight as this is. <hi>I ſee my Ieſus</hi> all of a gore blood, all his ſenſes,<note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of Chriſt one the croſſe expreſſed out of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fathers.</note> and faculties of bodye and ſoule, his partes and whole ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſmitten; I ſee that <hi>Angelicke head,</hi> at whoſe preſence the very powers of heauen weare wont to tremble, all to bee preaned and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14296:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> prickt through with thornes: I ſee that <hi>Diuine face</hi> that was fairer then the children of men, now defaced, and defiled with the ſpittle of the Iewes; I ſee thoſe <hi>Chriſtall eyes,</hi> once clearer then the Sunne beames, now blood-ſhed, and caſt ouer with the darkeneſſe of death; <hi>his eares</hi> once accuſtomed to the hymnes of Angelles, muſt now giue eare to the exclamations of Diuelles; <hi>his mouth</hi> once full of Butter and Hony to eate, is now full of Gall and viniger to drinke; <hi>his feete</hi> faſtened with Nayles to the Croſſe, and yet his verye ſoote-ſtoole, is holye: <hi>his handes and armes</hi> all ſpreade, and diſtreined on the Croſſe, and yet they framed and faſhioned the Heauens: <hi>his whole Man</hi> all torne, and wounded with laſhes and Whippes: his <hi>ſide</hi> broacht through with a Launce;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14296:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> and <hi>his hart bloode</hi> guſhing out on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide. <hi>Et quid plura?</hi> From the ſoale of his foote to the crowne of his head he reſerued nothing entire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.26. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos of the bleſſed Virgin.</note> ſaue onely his tongue therewith to pray for them, that perſecuted him, and commend his Mother vnto his diſciple; <hi>Woman beholde thy ſonne.</hi> O how may we conceaue? how did the hart of that <hi>bleſſed Mother and Virgin Mary,</hi> throb and beate then within her breaſt; O how much rather had ſhe, her bodie ſhould haue gone from her ſoule, then her ſonne and ſauiour gone out of her ſight? O how wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would ſhe haue eaten the afell gall, which her ſonne did eate, and dranke the ſower vineger,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 24.26.</note> which her ſonne did drinke? and giuen vp the ghoſt which her ſonne gaue vp, ſaue that he <hi>muſt needes die for the ſinnes of the world?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 31.1.</note> O my ſonne, and O the ſonne of my wombe, and O the ſonne of my deſires, O my ſonne <hi>Lemuel,</hi> O my ſonne <hi>Salomon;</hi> finally I cannot
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14296:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> expreſſe. <hi>Then ſinfull man that I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> who ſhall deliuer mee from this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſinne? It is my ſinne (I ſee) it is my ſinne that ſlew my Sauiour vpon the croſſe: my pride the thornes that pricked him: my gay-garments, &amp; gue-gawes the purple that mocked him: mine hypocriſie the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that blinde-folded him, I was that ſubtile Scribe, and proude Phariſee that entrapped him: that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous <hi>Iudas</hi> that betrayed him: that enuyous Iewe that accuſed him: that irreſolute man-pleaſing <hi>Pilate</hi> that condemned him: that bloudy exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner that hanged him; and yet alas I am euen now ready ſtill, ſtill, to crucifie my Chriſt againe.</p>
            <p>Out of this <hi>triple paſsion</hi> of Chriſt wee Chriſtians are to learne <hi>a three-foulde leſson,</hi> a leſſon of propaſſion,<note place="margin">A three-fold leſſon very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for all Chriſtians.</note> of paſſion, and of compaſſion. In our <hi>propaſsion</hi> wee may meditate in this manner, and it is in a manner a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion of Chriſt; Alacke, Alacke
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14296:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>The ſonne of God</hi> hath bene crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for mee (miſerable ſinner as I am) once afore, and why doe I thus with ſinne vpon ſinne daylie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6:6.</note> and hourelye <hi>Crucifie him againe,</hi> and make a mocke of him? O why ſhould I not rather <hi>Crucifie the world</hi> vnto my ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat:</hi> 6.14 <hi>Rom:</hi> 6.6. Ambroſe <hi>de vnica poenitent: Dan.</hi> 9.4.5.7.9.</note> and my ſelfe vnto the worlde? O why doe I thus <hi>Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riate</hi> in the bloode of Chriſt? <hi>O Lord God</hi> I haue ſinned, I haue ſinned: <hi>Righteouſneſſe and compaſsion</hi> is thine (O Chriſt) and mine is open ſhame, and confuſion:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lament:</hi> 1.16. <hi>Lament:</hi> 2.11.3:48.</note> 
               <hi>For theſe thinges</hi> I weepe: Mine <hi>eyes</hi> daye and night caſt out <hi>riuers of teares:</hi> My Bowels ſwell: my liuer is powred vpon the earth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> 3.41</note> And now I lift vp mine <hi>heart and handes</hi> vnto thee (O King of Heauen) <hi>O Lorde heere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan:</hi> 9.19.</note> O Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue: O Lorde conſider, and doe it: Haue mercie vpon mee for thine owne ſake, euen for thy name ſake (my God and my Chriſt) for thy name is called vpon me.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:14296:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Of our <hi>paſsion</hi> we may ponder in this ſenſe with our ſelues:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.21</note> 
               <hi>Quaeſtionleſſe hereunto</hi> are we called. For <hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo <hi>ſuffred</hi> for vs, leauing vs an <hi>ensa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple</hi> that wee ſhould alſo <hi>ſuffer</hi> for him. <hi>Caedi Chriſtianorum eſt,</hi> (ſaide an holye man) <hi>caedere Pilati et Caiphae:</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt hath drunke to vs already, if wee will bee Chriſtians wee muſt all pledge him in the ſame cuppe.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>13.15</hi> Luc: <hi>9.23.</hi> Iſaiah. <hi>50.6 W: Th:</hi> à Campis de Regia via ſanctae crucis.</note> 
               <hi>I haue</hi> giuen you (ſaith hee) an example: <hi>Tolle crucem, et ſequere me:</hi> I haue giuen my backe to the <hi>ſmiters,</hi> my cheekes to the <hi>nippers,</hi> my face as a flint againſt ſpitting, and ſhame: And the <hi>Diſciple</hi> (you know) is not aboue his <hi>Maiſter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.24.</note> If therefore you are my Diſciples? <hi>Take vp my Croſſe</hi> and followe mee.<note place="margin">Luc. <hi>9.2.3. D.D.</hi> Carth Amator: Mundi: Speculum.</note> 
               <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Carthuſian</hi> in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe intitled <hi>a Looking-Glaſſe for the louers of this world</hi> hath an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſaying to this praeſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <hi>Nemo potest venire de feſto ad feſtum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:14296:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>No man (ſaith hee) may haue his feaſt here and his feaſt there to. <hi>If we will</hi> raigne there, we muſt ſuffer here.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thou therefore ſuffer</hi> afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as a good Souldier of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
            <p>But as wee muſt ſuffer, ſo muſt we ſuffer (if the will of God be ſo) ſo as hee did;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17</note> 
               <hi>Better it is</hi> we ſuffer for wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, then for euill doing. <hi>Mori volo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hegeſippus</hi>) in his 3. booke, and 17.<note place="margin">Hegeſipp: de bello Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daico. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> Chapt. <hi>ſed vt Hebraeus:</hi> I am content to ſuffer but as <hi>a Martyr,</hi> not as a murtherer, or a theife: I am content to be a <hi>doore-barred</hi> to death,<note place="margin">Doroth: de Prophet: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt: Septu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agint: &amp;c.</note> but as <hi>Amos</hi> was: to be ſawen in peeces, but as <hi>Eſay</hi> was: to bee ſtoned, but as <hi>Ieremye</hi> was: to bee caſt to the Lyons, but as <hi>Daniel:</hi> to the Sworde, but as <hi>Paule:</hi> to the Croſſe, but as Chriſt: I would dye, but as an Hebrew, and like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and for Chriſte, and ſo come when thou wilt, <hi>Salua ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta crux.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14296:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Of our <hi>compaſsion</hi> wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue in like Chriſtian ſort, and this wee extend to our crucifiers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iud.</hi> 9:</note> and exemplyfie thus; <hi>The Archangell Michael, when</hi> hee diſputed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> with the Diuell himſelfe, durſt not intreate him with any curſed language, but ſaide; The <hi>Lorde rebuke</hi> thee Sathan: How is it then that wee againſt our bretheren are ſo bloudylie bent, to take the ſtaffe indeede out of Gods owne hand,<note place="margin">Vengeance is mine. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 12.19. <hi>Act:</hi> 7.60:</note> and for euery trifle to crie; <hi>Reuenge?</hi> The Protomartyr Saint <hi>Stephen, when the Iewes</hi> ſtoned him to death kneeled downe, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>Lorde laie not this ſinne</hi> to their charge: how is it then that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not learne this leſſon of him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math:</hi> 5.44 Collect on <hi>S. Stephens</hi> day.</note> 
               <hi>to loue our enimies, to praye</hi> for our <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors?</hi> The Archangell of all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, and <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> our Lorde and Maiſter Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, when hee was <hi>reuiled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2:23</note> 
               <hi>hee
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14296:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> reuiled</hi> not againe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet. the</hi> 2 23.</note> when he ſuffered, be threatned not againe, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.34.</note> that iudgeth righteouſly, eyther praying; <hi>father forgiue</hi> them, they know not what they doe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach:</hi> 3.2. <hi>Iud.</hi> 9.</note> or ſaying at moſt; The <hi>Lorde rebuke thee</hi> Sathan, euen the Lorde, that, hath choſen Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, rebuke thee: How is it then,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ:</hi> 3.12.13.</note> that, <hi>as the elect</hi> of God, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and like Chriſtians, wee put not on theſe bowelles of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of long ſuffering, of mercies, of kindeneſſe, of meekeneſſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another, and forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one another, if any man hath a quarrell to another? euen as Chriſt hath doone, euen ſoe doe wee.<note place="margin">The third diuiſion of the third generall circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance the third &amp; laſt diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> O Compaſſe mee (ſweete Ieſus) with this thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly I willed you to beholde him in his <hi>Seſsion, and interceſsion,</hi> and that with the <hi>eye of affiance</hi> and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14296:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numbr.</hi> 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>In the one &amp; twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tith of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> when as the people of Iſrael were ſtung to death for their ſinnes with fiery Serpents, It is written that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> by the commaundement of God erected a Serpent of Braſſe for a ſigne; and when a Serpent had bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a man, then he looked vp to the Serpent of Braſſe, and liued.</p>
            <p>The ſignification, or moral of which myſtery, <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> in his Goſpell and thirde Chapter: dooth plainely ſet downe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn:</hi> 3.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>As Moſes lift vp the Serpent</hi> (ſaith he) in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: euen ſo muſt the ſonne of man be lift vp, that whoſoeuer <hi>beholdeth him</hi> and <hi>beleeueth on him,</hi> doe not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe then whole generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Vipers, all the fierye Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes of thy ſinnes enuyron thee on euerye ſide: the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of couetouſneſſe frette thee: the flame of concupiſcence burne thee, the prickles of pride ſtinge
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14296:33"/> thee to death; ſtraight wayes <hi>for thy comfort,</hi> thou knoweſt what thou haſt to doe: make vp by the wing of faith, to that <hi>ſanctified ſerpent</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, and thou art ſaued: the ſigne of that ſerpent wil eaſilie breake this ſerpents head.</p>
            <p>Now I beſeech you brethren by the mercifulneſſe of God, attend now vnto this which I ſhall ſay vnto you, and embrace I pray you this <hi>Doctrine of conſolation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods Elect.</note> with a right hand as I entend it you. We read oft-times in the volume of this booke, a certaine challenge as it were ſent downe from that righteous iudge vnto all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the earth; If any man durſt ſtand in iudgement with him. <hi>Now therefore (O inhabitants</hi> of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem) and men of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 5.3.</note> iudge I pray you (ſaith he) betweene me and my vineyard; for I will be tryed by your ſelues.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 16.21.</note> O Lord, <hi>Oh if a man</hi> might plead with God, O Lord thou art I know a ſeuere, yet righteous iudge, I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14296:33"/> know, thou knoweſt my very heart &amp; reines; yet (if ſo it ſeeme good in thine eyes) I, as ſinfull a man, as I am, euen I am content to enter into iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thee; Yea in the name of Chriſt Ieſus I waxe confident and bold, let all the diuels in hell accuſe me; all their Angels beare true or falſe witneſſe againſt mee; mine owne conſcience co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne me; thine owne ſelfe, <hi>ſecundum allegata et probata,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in iudgement againſt me; On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let me be weighed but <hi>in a iuſt bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 31.6.</note> and I will iuſtifie my ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and yet will neuer appeale from thee; I will be tryed by thine owne ſelfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 50.8. <hi>Iob.</hi> 33.6.</note> For let me ſee <hi>who will</hi> contend in <hi>Gods ſteed</hi> with me? Let vs ſtand together: who is mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie? let him come neere to me, what can he lay to my charge? A matter of haughtineſſe perchance, or an high looke? I confeſſe that, and more toe: But <hi>Ecce homo,</hi> Behold this man; And ſo I haue recompenced
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14296:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> that with the humilitie of my Ieſus. Some reuelling perchance, or ſome riot? I grant that too But <hi>Ecce homo: Behold this man:</hi> and ſo I haue ſalued that ſore with the ſobrietie of my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. A murder it may bee? or a robbery, or ſomething worſe? be it as bad, as bad may be, my prayer and plea ſhall alway be the ſame, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Ieſu reſponde pro me,</hi> O my Lord Ieſus anſwer for me, and <hi>Ecce homo,</hi> behold this man: And why did he die the death but for this:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Méſhichca. Pſ.</hi> 84.9.</note> 
               <hi>O looke vpon the face</hi> of thy Chriſt. <hi>Turba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur conſcientia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard: in Cant. Serm: <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non perturbatur, quia vulneru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini recordabor;</hi> O hide me in the holes of thy wounds.</p>
            <p>I diſpute not of the torment &amp; paine of his paſſion, whether ſolie in bodie, or partly in ſoule; it is the infinite me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and price of his paſſion, in reſpect of the perſon or ſubiect that ſuffered which I ſpeake of; Euery drop of his blood ſufficient to had redeemed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14296:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> ten thouſand worlds; then whereat ſhall we prize the Ocean thereof? <hi>Quod libet finitum</hi> (they ſay) <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumcunque magnum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alphonſ: Thoſtat: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulenſ: pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox: <hi>5.45</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in infinitum exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur ab eo, quod eſt infinitum:</hi> Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is finite (of what quantitie ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be) compare it with that which is infinite, and it is alwayes excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded infinitely. Collect then all thy ſinnes, whereof thou haſt, or maieſt be guiltie, from the day of thy birth to the houre of thy death, thy ſinnes originall and actuall, thy ſinnes in thought, worde, and worke: and not thine owne onely, but mine, and thine, and the ſinnes of all men vpon the face of the earth: and not of men onely but of Angelles too: <hi>Lucifer</hi> I meane and all his fellow Angelles, that fell from heauen: and not of them onely, but of <hi>Beelzebub</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all the damned diuels in hell.</p>
            <p>Collect (I ſay) all theſe three worlds
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14296:35"/> of ſinne into one head, <hi>as they</hi> fable that helliſh Dog had three heads on one necke; nay were it poſſible that heauen, earth, hell, and all, might be put in the one ballance, and the alone merit of Chriſt his paſſion might be poiſed in the other, they ſhould all appeare in compariſon of it, but as a drop of water to the ſeas, as the earth, to the heauens, as a very nothing to to the whole world. The ſumme of all is this; the mercies of Chriſt, and merits of his paſſion are in multitude innumerable, in magnitude immea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable, euery way vnvaluable and infinite.</p>
            <p>One the other ſide, the ſinnes of men, though to the vnderſtanding of man they may ſeeme infinite: yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and in the apprehenſion of God they are all finite both in number and meaſure. Well then Chriſt hath ſuffered once for all;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18</note> 
               <hi>the iuſt</hi> for the vniuſt: hee hath payed the price of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14296:35"/> our ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.14</note> &amp; why ſhould we be ſued in the lawe? He, my ſuretie, hath <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled the hand writing</hi> on the croſſe, he hath made full ſatiſfaction already, &amp; why ſhould I, the debter, make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againe? It is againſt all lawe, and reaſon in the worlde, ciuill, Canon, common law and common ſenſe too, that there ſhould be two <hi>adaequate</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties inflicted for one,<note place="margin">F. de Reg: iur: l: bona fides. Innocent: de ſacro Altaris my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio. <hi>4.41.</hi>
               </note> and the ſame fault. <hi>Bona fides non patitur, vt bis idem exigatur.</hi> There is no ſuch iniquitie with men, and ſhall wee ſay there is more vnrighteouſneſſe with God? God forbid.<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the whole with Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.34.35. <hi>Ieſus adeſt, totum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt. De familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri amicitia Ieſu.</hi> W. Th: <hi>à cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quia ergo Iuſtus iniuſtè punitus eſt, Iniuſtus iuſtè ſum libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My concluſion</hi> is then, <hi>there is</hi> no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>It is my Ieſus</hi> that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth mee, and who is he that can condemne me? It is my Chriſt that dyed for me, or rather that is riſen againe, and hath his <hi>ſeſsion</hi> at the right
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14296:36"/> hand of God, and maketh <hi>Interceſſion</hi> for mee; and who ſhall ſeperate mee from the loue of Chriſt?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</note> In a word <hi>the foundation</hi> of God remaineth ſure and hath this ſeale; <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his;</hi> and (as it is aeternally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in this indiſſolluble chaine) <hi>Whom once he knoweth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29.30.31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> he alſo <hi>praede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinateth,</hi> and whom he praedeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth he <hi>calleth,</hi> and whom he calleth he <hi>iuſtifyeth,</hi> and whom he iuſtifieth he <hi>glorifieth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall I then ſaye to theſe things? If God bee on my ſide, who can bee agaynſt mee? Hee hath giuen his owne onely ſonne for mee, and how can hee not giue with him all other things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee?</p>
            <p>As I ſaide afore, ſo ſay I nowe againe. <hi>The foundation of God</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſure, and hath this ſeale: <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19</note> Yea I know (and I hope to praeſume thus of the grace of God is not pride in mee,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14296:36"/> but faith) I my ſelfe knowe that <hi>my redeemer liueth,</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt is mine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.25.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Vſurpo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi ex viſceri bus Ieſu mei: Bern: in Cant: Serm: <hi>61:</hi>
               </note> and that the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of Ieſus is my Righteouſneſſe,</hi> and therefore if Chriſt bee ſaued, (which who dares doubt?) I hope I am as ſure I ſhall be ſaued with him, as that I am in this place.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>&amp;c. Rom:</hi> 8.38.39.</note> Yea <hi>verily I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> (and it is the ſpirite of God, that telles mee ſo within) that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther life, nor death, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things praeſent, nor things to come, nor perſecution, nor famine, nor plague, nor Spaniard, nor Pope, nor Diuell, nor any other creature, nor all the world ſhall euer ſeperate me from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
            <p>This is my <hi>doctrine of conſolation,</hi> this <hi>my demonſtration of faith:</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt this the gates of Hell ſhall neuer praeuaile, and the gates of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen cannot ſtand ſhut.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:14296:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>One little more</hi> yet of your patience, and I will onely commend this one hiſtory vnto your good remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and ſo recommende you vnto God. The ſtory is of <hi>Pilate.</hi> It is regiſtred by <hi>Mathew</hi> of Weſtminſter and others, that <hi>when Pilate</hi> was conuented before <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den legend in the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt.</note> for that he had done to death this innocent man, hee put on the coate of Chriſt, which was (as you reade) without ſeame; At the ſight whereof the Emperour, who was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe much incenſed, aroſe vnto him, ſaluted him, and euerye wayes kindely entreated him. Anon, when <hi>Pilate</hi> againe with his good leaue was departed, <hi>Tiberius</hi> againe was enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged more then euer before: he ſwears if euer he tooke him againe <hi>Quòd fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us mortis eſſet,</hi> there ſhould be but one way with him, and ſends out a freſh his Purſyuantes for him. <hi>Pilate</hi> againe returnes vnto him: <hi>Tiberius eftſoones</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of what he would doe, falles to embracing of him, and had not the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14296:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> powre to ſpeake as much as one hard word to him. All that were there did wonder at it, and <hi>Tiberius</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe did wonder at it; and if it bee true, I wonder at it too; and ſo may all you. But <hi>the legend</hi> it ſelfe ſaies this is no goſpell; yet marke mine <hi>Application. We haue all,</hi> euen the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beſt of vs all, we haue all plaied <hi>Pilate,</hi> we haue crucified, and crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againe the Lord Ieſus; the time wil come, when we muſt come to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for this; not as <hi>Pilate</hi> did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> an earthly Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, but before the <hi>King of Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.16.</note> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> the God of heauen and earth: we ſhall be able then, as of our ſelues, to anſweare no more for our ſelues, then <hi>Pilate</hi> was then, not one for a thouſand. What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth then, but that againe we play <hi>Pilate?</hi> But that wee put on vpon vs the coate of Chriſt? It will be that at the ſight thereof that iuſt God, who is angrie with vs, will be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14296:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14296:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:14296:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14296:39"/>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14296:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:14296:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:14296:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:14296:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:14296:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> well pleaſed with him, and for him with vs. If I may but touch his veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture onely, nay if I may but touch the outmoſt fillet or hem of his veſture, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaid the <hi>woman</hi> then ſicke of our <hi>Now-diſeaſe</hi> I ſhall be ſafe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.20.21. Then raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the bloudy flux in England.</note> But it is giuen vnto vs, not to touch his veſture onely, but to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it, and take holde of the whole cloath to; and not that onely, but to <hi>put on</hi> to,<note place="margin">Rom: <hi>13.14</hi> Galat. <hi>3.27.</hi> Eph. <hi>4.24.</hi> &amp;c: Qui am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectitur Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur in ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum. <hi>W: Th:</hi> à Camp: De Amore Ieſu. Iſaiah. <hi>43.2</hi>
               </note> not the coate, but <hi>Chriſt, to be inueſted</hi> in him, in corporate, and infleſhed in him, imboſſomed in him, euen to dwell in his boſome, as hee dwelleth in the boſome of his father <hi>Gremioque in Iaſonis haerens Per freta longa ferar, nihil illum amplexa vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor.</hi> I, <hi>my ſoule,</hi> ſhall paſte with thee through <hi>the waters of deſtruction,</hi> and they ſhall not drowne me: through the <hi>fire of Gods iudgement,</hi> and it ſhall not burne mee: I will feare no euill for <hi>thou art with me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. <hi>23.5.</hi> Tephillah le Thoren.</note> Nowe I pray God giue me grace, that when this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14296:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſoule of mine ſhall returne to God, that gaue it, it may couragiouſlye mount vp out of this earthly taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and take holde of this ancker of hope, with the ſame reſolution, and confidence, as I now preach it vnto you.<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh letanis.</note> And <hi>I beſeech thee</hi> (ſweete Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) euen by thine <hi>Agonie and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſweat, by thy croſſe and paſsion, by thy glorious Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, and Seſsion and interceſsion</hi> at the right hand of God, when in that dreadfull day of Iudgement, he ſhall preaſſe me with this, or this, or this enormitie, that then thou wouldeſt praeſent thy ſelfe vnto thine angrie father, in ſuch freſh and bleeding wiſe, as thou wert on the croſſe, and pleade for me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 43.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſay, <hi>Father, Ecce Homo: Beholde I am the man: I haue redeemed him: I haue anſwered for him: He is mine, Amen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.20. <hi>Attah Tag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanch. Pſ.</hi> 38.15. <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.46.</note> 
               <hi>Euen ſo come Lord Ieſus:</hi> It is thou, it is thou that <hi>haſt anſwered for me</hi> O Lord my Chriſt. <hi>Father into thy hands</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:14296:43"/> I commend my ſpirit.<note place="margin">A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Acts.</hi> 7.59. <hi>Num.</hi> 6.24.25. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Lorde Ieſus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord bleſſe vs,</hi> and keepe vs: the Lord make his face ſhine vpon vs, and be mercifull vnto vs: and lift vp his countenance vpon vs, and ſend vs peace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Corinth:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.13.</note>
               <hi>The Grace of our Lord Ieſus Christ,</hi> and the loue of God, and the communion of the holy Ghoſt, be with vs all euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
